Guide to the McGee Family Papers, 1857-2016 and undated RL.10042
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
McGee family papers
1857-2013 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
McGee family
RL.10042
25 Linear Feet
4.95 Gigabytes
John Sidney and Doris Thompson McGee were Baptist missionaries to Iwo, Igede-Ekiti, and Ikogosi, Nigeria from 1945-1977. They had two children, John David and Sidney. The McGee Family Papers represent the life work of two missionaries, John Sidney and Doris McGee. John and Doris were appointed to Nigeria in 1945 by the Foreign Mission Board of the Southern Baptist Convention, and served eight consecutive tours of service. The current collection contains collection information, correspondence between the McGee family members as John and Doris served in Nigeria, as well as correspondence between other missionaries, the personal papers of Doris, John S. and John David McGee, printed materials and publications about mission work and life in Nigeria (including books authored by members of the McGee family), hundreds of photographs related to the McGee's work, and audio-visual materials.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Original audiovisual materials are closed to use; contact Research Services in advance to request the production of listening copies.
However, collection may contain materials to which the Acknowledgment of Legal Responsibilities and Privacy Rights form applies. Patrons must sign this form before using this collection.
In addition, original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Some use copies are available in the collection. Otherwise, Research Services staff need to produce use copies before contents can be accessed.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 24-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Electronic records in this collection have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact Research Services before coming to use these records.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The McGee Family Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in August 2011, August 2013, and July 2016.
Biographical and Historical Note
John Sidney (1913-1999) and Doris (1918-1998) McGee were appointed on April 11th, 1945 by the Foreign Mission Board of the Southern Baptist Convention to Nigeria, where they served eight consecutive terms. Their primary role was that of "missionary advisors," or "field evangelism" for church development. They served at the Baptist College of Iwo from 1945-1948, and then at the Baptist Mission in Igede-Ekiti (Western Nigeria) and Ikogosi from 1949-1977. In 1956, they helped establish the sixth Baptist high school in Nigeria: the Ekiti Baptist High School, in Igede. In 1957, they were made "Chief Gbaiyegun of Igede," by the Onigede and Chiefs of Igede-Ekiti. In 1961, they were made paramount chief by the Ewi of Ado, on behalf of the Ekiti Baptist Association. In 1977, they were made "Chief Akorewolu of Ikogosi" by Loja and Chiefs of Ikogosi-Ekiti. The couple retired in 1978 after thirty-three years of missionary service.
John Sidney and Doris had two sons, John David (b. 1943) and Sidney (b. 1948). The McGees' children stayed with them in Nigeria until John David returned to the US for high school in 1958, where he stayed with a foster family. Much of the correspondence between family members takes place when the McGee children are in the United States to finish their education.
Collection Overview
This collection involves five main series: Collection Information, Correspondence, Personal Papers, Printed Materials and Publications, Visual Materials, and Audio-Visual Materials.
The Collection Information Series was compiled by John David McGee, and it provides a detailed guide to using the McGee Family Papers. It includes lists and details of all series in the collection, background information on the family, a list of Baptist missionaries in Nigeria, and a thorough history of the Baptist Mission in Nigeria.
The Correspondence Series includes early correspondence between John S. McGee and Doris Thompson, as well as Doris Thompson and her mother and later correspondence between members of the McGee family as they were separated during various Nigerian tours. Letters from Nigerian friends and missionary kids are also included. Letters deal with a variety of subjects, including life in Nigeria and daily occurrences as a missionary, John David's academic, career, and life plans, and arrangements for visits to Nigeria.
The Personal Papers Series includes three subseries: Doris McGee, John S. McGee and John David McGee. Amongst Doris McGee's personal items are prayer diaries that span almost her entire life, attendance and report cards, diplomas and awards, her personal writings and poems, items concerning her death and various miscellaneous items such as personal correspondence with friends and historical items concerning their time in Africa. Included in John S. McGee's personal papers are diplomas and certificates, a personal diary, address books and contact lists, his personal writings and notes, and articles concerning his death. John David McGee's personal items include early homework and report cards, diplomas, documents pertaining to soccer and the U.S. Soccer National Federation, and professional references and C.V.s.
The Printed Materials and Publications Series includes five subseries: printed materials by the McGee family members, books from the library of John S. and Doris McGee, books from the library of John David McGee, printed materials by other authors, and Baptist Mission to Nigeria Minutes. The McGee family publications include bound notebooks from John S. McGee's early life, published books and memoirs, and a case study written by Erin McGee after her visit to Nigeria. Also included are several religious pamphlets and texts authored and arranged by Doris McGee. Books from the library of John S. and Doris McGee are relevant to their personal life and history and include numerous bibles, high school and college yearbooks. Books from the library of John David McGee include books focusing on the history of the Baptist Mission to Nigeria, general books on Africa, and several Yoruba dictionaries. The other authors subseries includes diaries of other Nigerian missionaries, books about African missionaries and books about life in Africa. The Baptist Mission to Nigeria Minutes include bound volumes of the annual minutes of the missionary meeting, from 1950 to 1998.
The Visual Materials series is composed of four subseries: slides, photo albums, mounted photographs, and foam-core mounted photographs. The slides subseries contains hundreds of slides of photographs from the McGee family's time in Nigeria. The slides are all numbered and grouped into several major categories (listed below) and a description of each picture can be found in the Collection Information Series. The photo albums include pictures of John S. and Doris McGee's early life in college, seminary and early Nigeria, John David's baby years, a missionary trip to Brazil, and other family pictures. The mounted photographs were furnished by Foreign Mission Board and were taken in various missionary camps in Nigeria. The foam-core mounted photographs include memorial photos of John S. and Doris McGee, various early photos, John S. and Doris McGee with their grand- and great-grandchildren and the last photographs before John S. and Doris' deaths.
Slides 000-999: Missionaries and Missionary Kids ("MKs")
Slides 1000-1999: Nigerians
Slides 2000-2999: Baptist Mission Churches
Slides 3000-3999: Baptist Mission Schools
Slides 4000-4999: Baptist Mission Medical Work
Slides 5000-5999: General Life Scenes
Slides 6000-7999: Places/Locations
Slides 8000-8999: Mission Stations
Slides 9001-9999: Family/Personal
The Audio-Visual Materials Series includes several recordings and films taken by the McGee family members of various tours in Nigeria. The films range from 1945 to 2009, and span the three generations of McGee missionaries. Also included is a DVD about the Conferment of Chieftaincy on John David McGee. The audio materials include several recordings of John and Doris McGee telling their life stories, talking about missionary work in Nigeria (especially regarding Baptist churches), and their first tour. The reel-to-reel tapes include audio-recordings of the McGee family as they were separated during various Nigerian tours. Ten super-8 film reels document John David McGee's trips to Nigeria from 1972 to 1983, which were the video source for the DVDs and video-cassette tapes.
This collection also contains seven USB thumb drives containing digital copies of many documents and slides. These items have been transferred to a preservation server and are available for use in the reading room.
Separated Material
Baptist Mission to Nigeria Minutes: bound volumes of the annual minutes of the missionary meeting, dating from 1950 to 1998. These have been removed and cataloged separately.
Iwo (Nigeria); Nigeria -- Description and travel; Nigeria -- Social life and customs; Children of missionaries; Married people in missionary work; Missionaries -- Nigeria; McGee, John David; McGee, Doris Thompson; McGee family; Southern Baptist Convention. Foreign Mission Board; McGee, Sidney; McGee, John Sidney
- Collection Information, 2011-2016, 3 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Compiled by John David McGee, the Collection Information Series provides a detailed guide to using the McGee Family Papers. It includes lists and details of all series in the collection, background information on the family, a list of Baptist missionaries in Nigeria, and a thorough history of the Baptist Mission in Nigeria. The materials reflect both the 2011 and 2013 accessions.
  - Outline of collection overview (Box 1)
  - Detailed collection overview, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - McGee resume summaries (Box 1)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Electronic record consists of 1 document file (MS Word format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.05 gigabytes.
  - Missionary Lists: 1849-1969 (Box 1)
  - The Baptist Mission to Nigeria Legacy Collection: introduction and Overview (Box 1)
    Electronic records consist of 9 document files (MS Word and TXT formats) and 7 JPEG image files extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.01 gigabytes.
  - The Nigerian Baptist Legacy Project: introduction, history and overview, 3 folders (Box 1)
    Electronic records consist of 8 document files (MS Word format) and 1 HTML file extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.03 gigabytes.
  - Correspondence: list and transcriptions, 2 folders (Box 1)
    Electronic records consist of 36 document files (MS Word format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.72 gigabytes.
  - Correspondence: list and transcriptions, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - John S. McGee and Doris McGee's personal papers: list and transcription, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - John David McGee's personal papers: list and transcription (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets and publications: list and details (Box 3)
    Electronic records consist of 4 computer files: 2 document files (MS Word and PDF formats), and 2 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.001 gigabytes.
  - Slides: list and details, 2 folders (Box 3)
    Electronic records consist of 2 document files (MS Word format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.001 gigabytes.
  - Nigerian Missionary Kids (MKs): Facebook comments (Box 3)
  - An Intro Binder, 1980s; 2016 (Box 35)
- Correspondence, 1940-1999 and undated, 2 boxes
  Includes early correspondence between John S. McGee and Doris Thompson and Doris Thompson and her mother as well as later correspondence between members of the McGee family as they were separated during various Nigerian tours. Letters from Nigerian friends and missionary kids are also included. Letters deal with a variety of subjects, including life in Nigeria and daily occurrences as a missionary, John David's academic, career, and life plans, and arrangements for visits to Nigeria.
  - 1940-1943, John Sidney McGee to Doris Thompson (Box 4)
    Electronic records consist of 67 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.01 gigabytes.
  - 1945, Doris McGee to her mother (Box 4)
  - 1958-1960, parents to John David, 4 folders (Box 4)
    Electronic records consist of 303 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.07 gigabytes.
  - 1958-1960, John David to parents, 3 folders (Box 4)
    Electronic records consist of 120 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.04 gigabytes.
  - 1958-1961, Sidney to parents (Box 4)
    Electronic records consist of 21 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.005 gigabytes.
  - 1958-1964, Sidney to John David (Box 4)
    Electronic records consist of 52 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.01 gigabytes.
  - 1960-1964, parents to John David, 5 folders (Box 4)
    Electronic records consist of 324 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.08 gigabytes.
  - 1960-1965, John David to parents (Box 4)
    Electronic records consist of 212 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.07 gigabytes.
  - 1964-1965, parents to Sidney and John David (Box 4)
    Electronic records consist of 26 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.01 gigabytes.
  - 1964-1965, Sidney to parents (Box 4)
  - 1966-1968, parents to Sidney digital files, 0.03 Gigabytes
    Electronic records consist of 8 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.003 gigabytes.
  - 1967-1968, Sidney to John David digital files, 0.001 Gigabytes
    Electronic records consist of 4 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.001 gigabytes.
  - 1967-1969, parents to John David (Box 4)
    Electronic records consist of 217 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.11 gigabytes.
  - 1967-1976, Sidney to parents (Box 4)
    Electronic records consist of 78 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.02 gigabytes.
  - 1970-1973, John to John David and Cheri (Box 5)
    Electronic records consist of 68 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.02 gigabytes.
  - 1970-1976, John David to parents, 2 folders (Box 5)
    Electronic records consist of 174 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.05 gigabytes.
  - 1972, John David to Cheri and Cheri to John David digital files, 0.004 Gigabytes
    Electronic records consist of 12 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.004 gigabytes.
  - 1973-1974, John to John David and Cheri (Box 5)
    Electronic records consist of 80 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.02 gigabytes.
  - 1975-1977, parents to John David and Cheri (Box 5)
    Electronic records consist of 73 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.01 gigabytes.
  - 1977, from the missionaries on the occasion of the McGee's retirement (Box 5)
    Electronic records consist of 51 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.01 gigabytes.
  - 1957-1999, letters from Nigerian friends, 2 folders (Box 5)
    Electronic records consist of 100 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.03 gigabytes.
  - 1957-1995, missionary kids to John David, 2 folders (Box 5)
    Electronic records consist of 153 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.03 gigabytes.
  - Digitized cablegrams, 1962-1970
- Personal Papers, 1907-2013 and undated, 6 boxes
  This series includes three subseries: Doris McGee, John S. McGee and John David McGee.
  - Doris McGee
    Included amongst Doris McGee's personal papers are attendance and report cards from high school, diplomas and honorary awards, poems and notes, and items concerning her death. The (mainly prayer) diaries follow Doris McGee's early life in high school and college, her time in Nigeria, and her retired life in America. Also included are several financial journals (one of which dates to high school), typed portions and a topical organization of earlier diary entries.
    - Academics, 1933-1939 (Box 5)
    - Certificates and honors, 1935-1994 (Box 6)
      Electronic records consist of 8 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.001 gigabytes.
    - Personal diaries, 1934-1976, 4 folders (Box 6)
      Electronic records consist of 333 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.08 gigabytes.
    - Personal Diaries digital files, 1976-1982
      Electronic records consist of 95 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.03 gigabytes.
    - Personal diaries, 1982-1995, 3 folders (Box 7)
      Electronic records consist of 225 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.03 gigabytes.
    - Typed portions of the first diary started in Nigeria and a second part from 1965-1966, undated (Box 7)
    - Doris McGee diaries partial transcripts, 2013
      Electronic records consist of 3 document files (MS Word format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 500 kilobytes.
    - Financial journal, undated (Box 7)
    - Topical organization of previous diary entries, undated (Box 7)
    - Writings, 1987-1995, bulk undated, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Death, 1998, 2 folders (Box 8)
      Electronic records consist of 18 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.003 gigabytes.
    - Biographical-related data, 1946-1997 (Box 8)
      Electronic records consist of 3 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.001 gigabytes.
    - Items concerning Baptist history in Nigeria, 1950-1999 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence from friends, 1975-1991 (Box 8)
    - Personal correspondence, 1947-1999 (Box 8)
      Electronic records consist of 42 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.01 gigabytes.
    - Materials pertaining to Mars Hill reunion, 1989-1995, 1 folders (Box 8)
    - Materials pertaining to Mars Hill reunion, 1989-1995, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - John S. McGee
    Items in this series include diplomas and other honors; contact lists and address books of friends and missionaries; sermon notes, chapter notes and classroom notebooks; a diary; condolences for death of John S. McGee and items pertaining to his memorial.
    - Certificates and honors, 1949-1995 and undated (Box 9)
      Electronic records consist of 10 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.002 gigabytes.
    - Certificates and honors, 1968-1989, 1 folders (Box 30)
    - Diary, 1960 (Box 9)
      Electronic records consist of 1 MS Word document file extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.04 gigabytes.
    - John S. McGee's parents' marriage certificate, 1907 (Box 9)
      Electronic record consists of 1 JPEG image file extracted from USB thumb drive, 228 kilobytes
    - Digital Materials related to the retirement of John S. and Doris McGee, 1977; .004 Gigabytes
      Electronic records consist of 17 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.004 gigabytes.
    - Address books and contact lists, 1996 and undated, 4 folders (Box 9)
    - Items pertaining to the trust established by John S. and Doris McGee, 1985-1997 (Box 10)
    - Documents concerning the Mars Hill College gift return, 2011 (Box 10)
    - Writings, 5 folders (Box 10)
      Electronic records consist of 7 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.002 gigabytes.
    - Death, 2 folders (Box 10)
      Electronic records consist of 88 image files (JPEG and BMP format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.03 gigabytes.
    - John S. McGee personal correspondence, 1964-1965; 1991; 1997-1998
      Electronic records consist of 19 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.004 gigabytes.
  - John David McGee
    Items include homework, report cards, diplomas; correspondence with friends and family; documents pertaining to soccer, the U.S. Soccer National Federation and youth revival; and professional references, notes, C.V.s.
    - Academics, 1950-1984, 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Certificates and honors, 1943-1979 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence personal to John David McGee, 1961-2013, 3 folders (Box 11)
      Electronic records consist of 11 image files (JPEG format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.002 gigabytes.
    - Extracurricular activities, 1972-2010, 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Professional, 1991-2000 (Box 11)
    - McGee letters and correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 35)
    - McGee passport, 1948; 1952 (Box 35)
    - McGee Nigerian driver's permit, Summer 1960 (Box 35)
    - McGee personal items, 1960; 1984 (Box 35)
      Electronic records consist of 24 image files (JPEG and TIFF format) and 1 document (MS Word format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.08 gigabytes.
- Printed Materials and Publications, 1857-2010 and undated, 13 boxes
  The series includes five subseries: printed materials by the McGee family members, books from the library of John S. and Doris McGee, books from the library of John David McGee, printed materials by other authors, and Baptist Mission to Nigeria Minutes.
  - McGee Family
    Includes bound notebooks from John S. McGee's early life, published books and memoirs, and a case study written by Erin McGee after her visit to Nigeria. Also included are several religious pamphlets and texts authored and arranged by Doris McGee.
    - Notebook for Bible 210, by John S. McGee, 1941 (Box 12)
    - Notebook for Bible 221, by John S. McGee, 1941 (Box 12)
    - Paul and his Writings, by John S. McGee, 1942 (Box 12)
    - Notebook-Bible, by John S. McGee, undated (Box 12)
    - Concerning Preachers, by John S. McGee, undated (Box 12)
    - To His Glory, by Doris and John S. McGee, early 1990s, 2 copies (Box 12)
    - Various pamphlets and publications, arranged and authored by Doris McGee, undated, 4 folders (Box 13)
    - An Amazing Story, by John David McGee, 2009, 2 copies (Box 13)
      Electronic records consist of 6 document files (MS Word format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 1.18 gigabytes.
    - The Reminiscence: An Amazing Story, by John David McGee, 2009 (Box 14)
    - Confessions of a Professional Holy Man, by John David McGee, 2010 (Box 14)
      Electronic record consists of 1 document file (MS Word format) extracted from USB thumb drive, approximately 0.02 gigabytes.
    - Journal of Erin McGee, 1993 (Box 14)
    - Case Study: Life of Hansen's Disease Victims, Baptist Health Services, Ogbonnoso, Nigeria, West Africa, by Erin McGee, 1993 (Box 14)
    - Summer of 1962, by John David McGee, 2015-2016 (Box 35)
    - Summer of 1962 original documents, by John David McGee (Box 35)
  - Books from the library of John S. and Doris McGee
    These books were relevant to John S. and Doris McGee's personal life and history. Includes numerous bibles, high school and college yearbooks. Some books may include personal notes by Doris or John S. McGee.
    - Bible, Chain-Reference, 1935 (Box 14)
    - Bible, Revised Standard Version, 1962 (Box 14)